Register of the Charlotte Hoffman Kellogg papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charlotte Hoffman Kellogg papers
1916-1956
56029
Kellogg, Charlotte.
1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box, 1 oversize folder (2.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives. Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Charlotte Kellogg papers include speeches and writings, correspondence, printed matter, and scrapbooks relating to relief work in Belgium during World War I and in Poland during and after World War II, and to Queen Jadwiga of Poland.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1956.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Vernon Lyman Kellogg papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Paderewski Testimonial Fund records, Hoover Institution Archives
Commission for Relief in Belgium records, Hoover Institution Archives
Commission for Polish Relief records, Hoover Institution Archives
Jean Kellogg Dickie collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Kellogg-Dickie papers, Yale University Library Manuscripts and Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1874 Born, Grand Island, Nebraska
1900 Ph.B., University of California
1903-1907 English teacher, Anna Head's School in Berkeley, California
1908 Married Vernon Kellogg
1910 Daughter, Jean Kellogg, born in Berkeley, California
1910s or 1920s, circa Speaking tour for the U.S. Food Administration
1915 Organized the California Committee for Relief in Belgium and Northern France
1916 Worked for the Commission for Relief in Belgium
1917 Author, Women of Belgium: Turning Tragedy to Triumph
1918 Returned to Belgium and studied lace-making
1919 Traveled to Poland and studied the work of Polish women
1920 Author, Bobbins of Belgium
1921 Escorted Marie Curie to the United States
1928-1929, circa Campaigned for Herbert Hoover
1931 Author, Jadwiga: Poland's Great Queen
1939-1946, circa Chairman, Paderewski Testimonial Fund
1939-1948, circa Director, Commission for Polish Relief
1960 May Died
Sources:
Irene Alexander. "Carmel Highlands Resident Presents Banquet Cloth to Hoover Library," Peninsula Herald. May 23, 1955.
Guide to the Kellogg-Dickie Papers. Yale University Library Manuscripts and Archives. http://hdl.handle.net/10079/fa/mssa.ms.0626
Scope and Content of Collection
An author and relief worker, Charlotte Kellogg provided aid to the people of Belgium and Poland. In 1916, she traveled to Belgium to work with the Commission for Relief in Belgium (CRB), an organization directed by her husband, Vernon Kellogg. As an assignment for the CRB, Herbert Hoover asked Charlotte Kellogg to study the women of Belgium and publicize her findings. In addition to various articles, Kellogg published Women of Belgium: Turning Tragedy to Triumph, which contains an introduction by Herbert Hoover, and Bobbins of Belgium, which documents the Belgian lace industry. Many of the Speeches and writings in the collection reflect Charlotte's role as a relief worker and advocate, drawing from her experiences in Belgium. This file also includes a typescript of her book on Queen Jadwiga of Poland.
The Relief work file contains two scrapbooks, identical except for small formatting elements, which were given to Kellogg and the California Committee for Relief in Belgium by an orphanage in Charleroi, Belgium. The scrapbooks contain photographs and descriptions in French of the orphans, scenes from their daily lives, and scenes of destruction from World War I.
The Charlotte Hoffman Kellogg papers were originally part of the Vernon Lyman Kellogg collection, until documents related specifically to Charlotte were separated.
Source:
Irene Alexander. "Carmel Highlands Resident Presents Banquet Cloth to Hoover Library," Peninsula Herald. May 23, 1955.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Commission for Relief in Belgium (1914-1930).; International relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.
Collection Contents
- Speeches and writings, 1917-1956 (Box 1)
  Includes typescripts, clippings, reprints, and correspondence. Arranged chronologically.
  - "Address by Mrs. Charlotte Kellogg." Speech before the Canadian Club of Ottawa, 1917 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Bobbins of Belgium, James Healy correspondence, 1917-1920 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Articles by Charlotte Kellogg, clippings and reprints, 1917-1926 (Folder 1: 3)
  - "A and E." Speech, circa 1919 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Jadwiga, Poland's Great Queen, typescript, 1931 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Bibliography, 1956 (Folder 1: 6)
- Relief work file, 1916-1948 (Box 1-2)
  Includes clippings, reports, scrapbooks, and awards. Arranged alphabetically by subject or format, with oversize materials at the end of the series.
  - Belgium, 1916-1917, undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Belgian lace clippings, circa 1917-1920 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Passports and travel documents, 1916 (Folder 1: 9)
    Includes certificate for Commission for Relief in Belgium
  - Poland, report of relief work, 1948 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Oversize materials (Folder 2, map case)
    - Médaille Commémorative du Comité National, Belgium certificate, 1919
    - Scrapbooks (Folder 2)
      - To Charlotte Kellogg from orphans in Charleroi, Belgium, 1920 (Folder 2)
        Includes clippings at end of bound volume
      - To the California Committee from orphans in Charleroi, Belgium, 1920 (Folder 2)